Abraham: With the large amount of
malware out there it will inevitably
penetrate and infect a system
especially a vulnerable system.
This infection maybe caused by downloading
a music file, a video file, or any
other software from suspicious sites.
Also clicking on a link from a
suspicious email sent from an unknown
email address or even one pretending
to be from a trusted contact.
The most common signs that a system
has been compromised are when a
computer slows down, browsers redirect
to other sites, infection warnings
and offers of software to buy to fix
it and pop-up ads, also, problems
shutting down and starting up a system.
Any of these may suggest
that a system is infected.
So how can you stop this happening?
Make sure that your system is protected by
legitimate 'anti-malware' purchased from
a reputable company even if it is a mobile
system and that it is kept up to date,
both the operating system and any software
installed on it such as your web browser.
Keep all devices secure and don't download
anything from any dodgy sites or click on
any unknown links on unreliable emails.
Only purchase from official suppliers.
But if you do find that you have
Malicious software infecting
your system, can it be removed?
It is possible to remove malware, by
running a scan using the security software
installed on the device or system and
taking steps to fix the web browser.
Anti-malware works in two different ways.
The first is a more outdated
approach which works on creating
a hash of all files on the system.
This hash is then checked against a list
of known malicious hashed of malware.
This is referred to as
signature-based detection.
The problem with this method is that
it relies on the fact that the malware
has been previously identified and
at the pace at which malware is being
developed this is becoming harder to do.
In response to this a lot of antimalware
solutions now work on a heuristic
detection method, which looks more at
the behaviours of files or processes
in a system to identify what could
be potentially malicious behaviour.
--
Nicole: So, what do you do
if your system gets infected?
The first step in incident response
if you are concerned that a device or
system may be infected is containment.
It’s important to disconnect from the
internet and the network you’re on as this
will prevent any more data being sent to
a malware server or will stop it spreading
to other computers on your network.
Stay offline as much as possible unless
needing to download any legitimate
tools to help get rid of the malware.
Disconnect after the download
is complete and stay offline
until the malware is removed.
Opening a system in safe mode or
safe boot allows only the minimum
software and programs to load.
Logging in to accounts should be
avoided whilst removing malware so
as not to expose passwords through
copy and paste function or by 'show
password' because 'key logger' malware
is a common component of malware.
Also avoid sharing any personal details or
information whilst a device is infected.
Check activity monitors for malicious
applications especially if a suspicious
update or application has been installed.
Run a malware scanner.
These can remove most standard infections
however if your antivirus software hasn't
already picked this up you should try
another scanner which may be able to
detect more existing and emerging malware
such as a heuristic antimalware solution.
Verify the browser homepage this will
involve connecting to the internet and
clear the cache, this is the temporary
storage location where data is saved.
If malware removal is unsuccessful,
it may be that the operating system
may need to be reinstalled along with
applications and programs from scratch.
If everything is backed up it shouldn't
be a problem but contacting the system
suppliers help desk may be necessary.
This process is exactly the same for large
companies and organisations but is usually
handled by tools that do these steps
or a dedicated incident response team.
In this video we have tended to focus
mainly on the single user, how their
system can become infected or suffer
an attack and what to do if it happens.
But often single users link to others
and the attack can gather pace amongst
their contacts, fellow workmates,
and businesses and organisations.
Abraham: Every individual is a
potential target of malicious software
attacks as well as every business or
organisation, no matter what the size.
By attacking one individual a threat actor
can have access to so many others and
the potential to access whole systems.